They're shutting down the biggest
science experiment in the world to build
something even cooler right here in
Switzerland. There's a huge tunnel 100 m
underground and 27 km long. And inside
that tunnel is a long blue tube. And
inside that tube, they put two pipes
that they keep colder and emptier than
outer space. And down those pipes, they
fire particles smaller than atoms in
opposite directions, pushing them faster
and faster until when they're almost
going the speed of light, they finally
smash together. And out of that
collision comes energy. And we know that
energy and mass are related. So,
sometimes that energy can turn into
physical mass, like rare or unknown
particles, like the Higgs boson, which
they discovered in 2012. But right now,
we only see the Higgs boson in about one
in a billion collisions. So, we need
more collisions. So, scientists are
upgrading this machine with stronger
magnets that push the particles closer
together and new tech to better align
increasing [music]
the number of collisions by a factor of
10. And it should be ready in 2030. But
how do they get those tiny little
particles to actually hit each other? To
see that, subscribe.